<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[gabll blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://gabll.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://gabll.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-22T22:52:50-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://gabll.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Gabll]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[gitgab@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Project Luther: web scraping and linear regression on box office movies data]]></title>
    <link href="http://gabll.github.io/blog/2015/02/01/project-luter-web-scraping-and-linear-regression-on-box-office-movies-data/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-01T16:14:46-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://gabll.github.io/blog/2015/02/01/project-luter-web-scraping-and-linear-regression-on-box-office-movies-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last two weeks at the <a href="http://www.thisismetis.com/data-science">Metis Data Science Bootcamp</a> were quite intense. We learned the basics of web scraping with two interesting and powerful Python packages, <a href="http://www.crummy.com/software/BeautifulSoup/">BeautifulSoup</a> and <a href="https://code.google.com/p/selenium/">Selenium</a>, how to analyse and manipulate dataframes with <a href="http://pandas.pydata.org/">Pandas</a> and theory/applications of linear regression models.<br/>
At the end, we realised and presented to the class an individual project based on &ldquo;movies data&rdquo;. Everyone tried to answer a different question, from predicting success of movies based on tv series to understanding the key factors that determine the success of trilogies. My project was about predicting the box office opening income during the first weekend and determing the additional opening revenues in case of changing the release season given the genre.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"><img src="http://gabll.github.io/images/model1.png" alt="Predicting opening income" /></p>

<p>A couple of lessons learnt: production budget and number of opening theaters play a important role in predicting the opening income, and sometimes the holiday season doesn&rsquo;t represent the &ldquo;best season&rdquo; in case of comedy or action films.</p>

<p>More insights in <a href="https://github.com/gabll/Metis-Luther/blob/master/Project_Luther_rev06.pdf">this presentation</a>; web scraping scripts and linear regression analysis in this <a href="https://github.com/gabll/Metis-Luther.git">GitHub repository</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello world!]]></title>
    <link href="http://gabll.github.io/blog/2015/01/12/first-post/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-12T15:49:47-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://gabll.github.io/blog/2015/01/12/first-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>First day at the <a href="http://www.thisismetis.com/">Metis Data Science Bootcamp</a>! We started with an interesting icebreaker game, the <a href="http://datascopeanalytics.com/what-we-think/2014/09/18/hipster-classifier-icebreaker">hipster classifier</a>, and setting up the developing environment for the next weeks (GitHub, Python packages, etc). And as a consequence of this, my first blog post!</p>

<p>This blog is hosted by <a href="https://pages.github.com/">GitHub pages</a>, using <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a> as a framework for generating static content. Basically, you have a repository in your computer cloned from GitHub, with a subdirectory where you can put all your blog post files written with the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown">markdown markup language</a>. Two simple commands, <code>rake generate</code> and <code>rake deploy</code>, will turn the markdown files in real HTML pages and push them into your GitHub hosting service.<br/>
Personalising template and layout is quite time consuming, but there is no need to edit css or scripts.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"><img src="http://gabll.github.io/images/octopress_github.png" alt="Github pages - Octopress" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
